

NICOLÒ PAGAN, Ph.D. ETH

ABOUT ME

I am a computational data science engineer with a multi-disciplinary background in the social, behavioural, and network sciences.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I have a strong passion for mathematical modelling of real-world problems. My primary research interests lie in the area of social media platform dynamics, where I explore the complex interplay between AI and human decision-making so that I can design effective interventions that foster social well-being.

KEYWORDS

Complex Systems, Social Networks, Human/Al decision-making, Algorithmic Fairness

Contact nicolo.pagan@uzh.ch | +41 (0)78 9458438 | (he/him)

Website https://nicolo-pagan.github.io/

EXPERIENCE

ACADEMIC

05.2021 - Present **Postdoctoral Researcher**, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics,

University of Zürich

Mentor Prof. Dr. Anikó Hannák

05.2021 - 11.2021 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, Social Networks Lab, Department of Humanities,

Social and Political Sciences, ETH Zürich

Mentor Prof. Dr. Christoph Stadtfeld

02.2021 - 05.2021 Lecturer, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics, University of

Zürich

PROFESSIONAL

05 / 2013 - 12 / 2015 Software Engineer and Research Consultant in Computational Fluid-

Dynamics (CFD). Ascomp AG (Zürich, Switzerland).

07 / 2012 - 08 / 2012 **Software Engineer Intern** at FLUXiM AG (Winterthur, Switzerland)

EDUCATION

2016 - 2021 Ph.D., Automatic Control Laboratory, Department of Information Technology and

Electrical Engineering, ETH Zürich

Thesis Modeling, analysis, and inference in social network formation

Advisor Prof. Dr. Florian Dörfler

2011 - 2013 M.Sc. in Computational Science and Engineering (5.45/6), EPF Lausanne

Thesis Coupling 1D system code OLGA with TransAT CFD

Advisors Prof. Dr. François Gallaire, Dr. Sylvain Reboux

2007 - 2010 **B.Sc. in Mathematical Engineering (110/110** cum Laude), Politecnico di Torino

Thesis Analysis of the car behaviour while transiting on an active speed bump

Advisor Prof. Dr. Luigi Preziosi

PUBLICATIONS

SELECTED

- N. Pagan*, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: A Classification of Feedback Loops and Their Relation to Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems, under Review at FAccT.
- N. Pagan, W. Mei, C. Li, and F. Dörfler: A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers, Nature Communications 12, 6865.
- N. Pagan and F. Dörfler: *Game theoretical inference of human behavior in social networks*, Nature Communications 10, 5507.

GRANTS

01 / 2022 - 12 / 2023 Ethical Auditing of Control S

Ethical Auditing of Control Systems Methods, Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF). Grant #180545. CHF 192'000.

HONORS AND AWARDS

| 2019 | Invited by the Department of Mathematical Sciences at Politecnico di Torino |
|------|--|
| | during the Department of Excellence 2018-2022 program: awarded a scholarship |
| 2011 | Erasmus program at EPF Lausanne. Awarded a scholarship |
| 2010 | Admitted to the 7th cycle of Alta Scuola Politecnica Educational program |
| 2007 | Rank 1st at the Engineering admission test at Politecnico di Torino: awarded a |
| | scholarship |
| 2007 | Scientific High School Diploma: awarded with special distinction and a |
| | scholarship |

INVITED TALKS

| 28 / 02 / 2023 | Social Computing: Bridging the Gap Between Technology and Human |
|----------------|--|
| | Interaction, Digital Society Initiative (DSI) Professors Presentations, Zürich. |
| 01/09/2022 | The Interplay Between Content Quality and Recommender Systems in Social |
| | Network Dynamics. Keynote at the Media Consumption Habits of Young People |
| | workshop, European Alliance of News Agencies (EANA), Zürich. |
| 15/07/2021 | A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers |
| | Doctoral course on Mining knowledge from complex network, Torino. |
| 12/12/2020 | A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers |
| | Dynamics in Social and Economic Networks, CDC, South Korea (online) |
| 21 /09 / 2020 | Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Autonomy |
| | Talk, IDSC, ETH Zürich (online). |
| 09 /06 / 2020 | Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Intelligent |
| | Control Seminar, Peking University (online). |
| 28 /11 / 2019 | Game Theoretical Inference of Human Behaviour in Social Networks, Workshop |

on Networks Dynamics in the Social, Economic, and Financial Sciences, Torino.

TEACHING

| 2022 | 2 Examiner of <i>Fundamentals of People Oriented Computing</i> , Department of | | |
|-------------|---|--|--|
| | Informatics, University of Zürich | | |
| 2021 | Lecturer of Social Computing, Department of Informatics, University of Zürich | | |
| 2019 - 2020 | Head Teaching Assistant of Game Theory and Control, Department of | | |
| | Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zürich | | |
| 2016 - 2019 | Head Teaching Assistant of Linear Systems Theory, Department of Information | | |
| | Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zürich | | |
| 2017 - 2018 | Head Teaching Assistant of Non-linear Systems and Control, Department of | | |
| | Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zürich | | |
| 2012 | Teaching Assistant of Informatics 2, Department of Informatics, EPF Lausanne | | |

SUPERVISING

| 03 / 2023 - present | Michael Blum, University of Zürich. Independent Study. |
|------------------------------|--|
| 05 / 2022 - present | Maria Helena Margareta Pelli and Andrianos Michail, University of Zürich. |
| , , , , , , , , | Master Project: A longitudinal study of emotions on Twitter chains of re-tweets |
| 03 / 2022 - 07 / 2022 | Jules Authier, ETH Zürich. Semester Project: <i>Analysis of the Closed-Loop</i> |
| | between Recommender Systems and Opinion Dynamics |
| 06 / 2021 - 11 / 2021 | Michael Blum, University of Zürich. Bachelor Thesis: Learning and success in |
| | chess: the role of openings patterns |
| 09 / 2020 - 04 / 2021 | Anna M. Maddux, ETH Zürich. Master Thesis: Behavior estimation in dynamic |
| | games |
| 05 / 2020 - 12 / 2020 | Cheng Li, ETH Zürich. Master Thesis: Data-driven analysis of the ranking-quality |
| | network formation model |
| 05 / 2017 - 08 / 2018 | Marco Buob, ETH Zürich. Semester Project: Dynamics of cooperative agents in |
| | social network formation: theory and simulation |
| 10 / 2017 - 02 / 2018 | Tomer Gidron, ETH Zürich. Semester Project: Centrality games in social and |
| | economic networks |
| 02 / 2015 - 08 / 2015 | Jiadong Bao, ETH Zürich. Master Thesis at Ascomp AG: Cathare-TransAT |
| | Coupling for the Prediction of Boron Dilution in the ROCOM Test Facility |
| 02 / 2014 - 08 / 2014 | Hassan Bahramian, Politecnico di Milano. Master Thesis at ASCOMP AG: |
| | Coupling 1D System Code with TransAT CFD |

REVIEW ACTIVITY

| Automatica, Chaos, Journal of Complex Networks, VLDB, IEEE Transactions on |
|--|
| Control of Network Systems |
| The Web Conference, International Conference on Computational Social Science |
| (IC2S2), ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency |
| (FAccT), Network Science Conference (NetSci), Complex Networks Conference, |
| European Control Conference (ECC), IFAC World Congress |
| IC2S2 2022 |
| |

INDEPENDENT COURSES

| 10 / 2021 | AI + X Summit Workshop, Zürich |
|-----------|--|
| 06 / 2020 | Data Science in Techno-Socio-Economic Systems Workshop, ETH Zürich and |
| | NYU Courant (online) |
| 11/2019 | Network Dynamics in the Social, Economic, and Financial Sciences Workshop, |
| | Politecnico di Torino |
| 06 / 2018 | Summer School on Economic Networks, Oxford |
| 10/2017 | Autonomous Decision-Making Workshop, ETH Risk Center, Zürich |
| | |

IT SKILLS

Software

| Foundational | Programming | Data Science | Web Tools |
|--------------|-------------|--------------|-----------|
| MacOS-Unix | C/C++ | Python | HTML |
| Windows OS | Bash | SQL/Pandas | CSS |
| MS Office | Fortran | TensorFlow | |
| iWork | Git | Matlab/R | |

LANGUAGES

Mother Tongue Italian
Other Languages English C2 | French B1 | German A2

APPENDIX

Full list of publications List of conference talks

REFERENCES

Prof. Dr. Anikó Hannák, Assistant Professor, Social Computing Group, Department of Informatics, University of Zürich hannak@ifi.uzh.ch

Prof. Dr. Florian Dörfler, Associate Professor, Automatic Control Laboratory, Department of Information Technology and Electrical Engineering, ETH Zürich dorfler@ethz.ch

PERSONAL INFO

APPENDIX

FULL LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

[J2] **N. Pagan,** W. Mei, C. Li, and F. Dörfler: *A meritocratic network formation model for the rise of social media influencers*, Nature Communications 12, 6865 (2021) **DOI**:10.1038/s41467-021-27089-8.

[J1] **N. Pagan** and F. Dörfler: *Game theoretical inference of human behavior in social networks*, Nature Communications 10, 5507 (2019) **DOI**:10.1038/s41467-019-13148-8.

Journal Articles (Under Review or in Preparation)

[J4] S. Ioneuscu, A. Hannák, and **N. Pagan:** *The Role of Luck in the Success of Social Media Influencers*, invited and submitted to Applied Network Science (2023). Manuscript available upon request.

[J3] A. Bouleimen, S. Cresci, **N. Pagan**, A. Hannák, S. Giordano: *Uncovering Italian Twitter Users' Reactions to Covid-19 Events: A Content Analysis*, invited to PLOS One (2023). Draft available upon request.

Conference Articles

[C7] N. Pagan*, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: A Classification of Feedback Loops and Their Relation to Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems, under review at FAccT (2023). Manuscript available upon request.

[C6] S. Ionescu, A. Hannák, and **N. Pagan**: *Striving as a Social Media Influencer: is Creating Great Content Enough?*, under review at FAccT (2023). Manuscript available upon request.

[C5] N. Lanzetti, F. Dörfler, and **N. Pagan**: The Impact of Recommendation Systems on Opinion Dynamics: Microscopic versus Macroscopic Effects, submitted to the IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) (2023). Manuscript available upon request.

[C4] A. Maddux, **N. Pagan**, G. Belgioioso, and F. Dörfler, *Data-Driven Behaviour Estimation in Parametric Games*, accepted at the 22nd World Congress of the International Federation of Automatic Control (2023) **DOI**:10.48550/arXiv.2202.01229.

[C3] S. Ionescu, **N. Pagan**, and A. Hannák: *Individual Fairness for Social Media Influencers*, The 11th International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications (2022) **DOI**:10.1007/978-3-031-21127-0_14.

[C2] J. Bao, S. Reboux, **N. Pagan**, and D. Lakehal: *Cathare-TransAT Coupling for the Prediction of Boron Dilution in the ROCOM Test Facility*, 16th International Topical Meeting on Nuclear Reactor Thermal Hydraulics, (2015).

[C1] S. Altazin, B. Perucco, **N. Pagan**, K. Lapagna, T. Lanz, R. Knaack, E. Knapp, B. Ruhstaller: *Multi-scale modeling of organic light-emitting devices*, SID Symposium Digest of Technical Papers (2013).

Extended Abstracts

[EA4] **N. Pagan***, J. Baumann*, E. Elokda, G. De Pasquale, S. Bolognani, and A. Hannák: *Closing the Loop: Feedback Loops and Biases in Automated Decision-Making Systems*, under review at IC2S2 (2023). Abstract available upon request.

[EA3] S. Ionescu, A. Hannák, and **N. Pagan**: The impact of users' homophily and recommendation biases on social network inequalities, under review at the International School and Conference on Network Science (NetSci) (2023).

[EA2] N. Pagan, W. Mei, and F. Dörfler: Emergence of Zipf's law among social networks influencers, IFAC Conference on Networked Systems (NecSys) (2022).

[EA1] **N. Pagan** and F. Dörfler: *Learning strategic behavior in social and economic networks*, The 7th International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications: book of abstracts, p.207-209 (2018).

Monograph

[Th1] **N. Pagan**, *Modeling*, *analysis*, *and inference in social network formation*, ETH Zürich Research Collection (2021). **DOI**: <u>10.3929/ethz-b-000501329</u>.

Media Coverage

[M3] <u>Mathematics: Investigating how social media influencers arise</u>, In: NatureAsia (2021).

[M2] What influences the rise of influencers?, In: Phys.org (2021).

[M1] N. Pagan <u>Can social network structure reveal human behavior?</u>, Behind the paper blog post at Behavioural and Social Sciences - Nature Research (2019).

LIST OF CONFERENCE TALKS

08 / 11 / 2022 Individual Fairness for Social Media Influencers,

11th International Conference on Complex Networks and their Applications, Palermo (Italy)

08/09/2021

A meritocratic network formation model for User-Generated Content based platforms, 5th European Conference on Social Networks, Naples (Italy)

12/12/2018

Learning strategic behavior in social and economic networks, 7th International Conference on Complex Networks, Cambridge (UK)

12/06/2018

Social network formation: from individual incentives to systemic stability, GameNet at NETSCI, Paris (France)

14/02/2018

From individuals decisions to emerging social structure, Infrastructure Resilience Conference, Zürich (Switzerland)